Guide to the Dan Carpenter Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Dan Carpenter Papers,
1880-1993.
Carpenter, Dan.
6.5 linear feet (16 document cases and 2 flat storage boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1467
6933410
The Hudson Guild Records document the institution from its origins in the 1890s, when it organized clubs for Chelsea boys, to its work a century later, when it provided a wide range of social services to West Side residents.
Biographical Note
Herschel Daniel "Dan" Carpenter was born March 28, 1908 in the farm community of Attica, Ohio. He attended local public schools and then matriculated at Denison University in Granville, Ohio, where he was awarded a Bachelor of Arts degree in 1931. Later that year he moved to New York City and took ajob as a boys' group counselor at Hudson Guild, a West Side settlement house established in 1895 by Ethical Culture Society leader John Lovejoy Elliott. Elliott viewed Hudson Guild's mission as an effort "to get the people of the district themselves to be the social workers and the regenerators of their own neighborhood... The purpose of the Guild is to bring about active co-operation between different individuals and different classes for a single aim -- that aim being an attempt to learn how to live in a city." Towards this end the settlement sponsored such activities as social clubs, health clinics, summer camping, arts education and vocational training. Hudson Guild promoted the democratic participation of its members in running the settlement through a "Clubs Council" that determined many institutional policies and programs, and also provided a forum for public debate of political issues. Carpenter worked enthusiastically at Hudson Guild and developed a strong professional relationship with Elliott. This bond was strengthened when in 1932 he married Elliott's niece, Marjorie Elliott.
In London, a similar increase in social problems led reformers in 1884 to establish the first settlement house, Toynbee Hall. The settlement model, originally distinguished by a commitment on the part of its college-educated volunteers to "settle" in working class communities in order to confront their problems first-hand and to contribute to the moral uplift of their neighbors, was quickly imported to the United States. In 1886 Stanton Coit, a devotee of Felix Adler's Ethical Culture movement and early observer of the experiment at Toynbee Hall, founded The Neighborhood Guild (later renamed University Settlement) on Manhattan's Lower East Side. Over the next several decades settlement houses were established in cities across the country, staffed largely by recent college graduates, many of them young women eager to take an active role in public life. American settlements sponsored such programs as kindergartens, day care, social clubs, health clinics, visiting nurses, summer camps, arts education and vocational training. They served as observation posts for sociologists, journalists, and other researchers of urban conditions. Many settlements provided forums for public debate of political issues, and galvanized popular opinion in support of progressive social legislation.
Carpenter complemented his work experience with graduate and professional training, receiving a certificate from the National Recreation School in 1932, and a Master of Arts degree from the New York University School of Education the following year. His responsibilities at Hudson Guild increased steadily as the hard times of the 1930s depression continued. He took primary responsibility for the settlement's participation in the Chelsea Recreation Committee, a community organization which pressured city government for the construction and upkeep of parks, playgrounds and athletic facilities. Carpenter closely observed Elliott's success in organizing the Chelsea Association for Planning and Action, which galvanized community support for public housing construction on the West Side. Work on what would eventually be called "Elliott Houses" was begun just prior to Elliott's death in 1943. Soon after, Dan Carpenter was appointed the second Head Worker (the title was later changed to Executive Director) of Hudson Guild. Under his leadership during the war years Hudson Guild hosted USO activities, sponsored social programs for Coast Guard men encamped in the open field created by the temporarily halted public housing construction, cultivated food in "Victory Gardens" at its New Jersey camp facility, and initiated a veterans consultation service to help returning servicemen adjust to life at home. With the opening of Elliott Houses in 1947, Hudson Guild sharpened its focus to meet the needs of a changing Chelsea population. New programs for senior citizens were created, as well as a child care center and a mental health clinic. During the 1950s New York's Puerto Rican population increased dramatically, and many thousands of these new immigrants settled on the west side. Carpenter traveled to Puerto Rico to learn about the culture of the settlement's new neighbors. He added Spanish speakers to the settlement staff, and instituted English language instruction
One frustrating episode in this period was a collaboration with the controversial, pugnacious community organizer Saul Alinsky. The Chelsea Citizen Participation Project, co-sponsored by Hudson Guild and Alinsky's Industrial Areas Foundation, succeeded in convening a "Chelsea Community Council" comprised of representatives from dozens of local organizations eager to participate in the planning of additional urban renewal and social service activities for the neighborhood. Unfortunately, disagreements arose among members regarding the Council's internal organization and policies, and an acrimonious public debate culminated in the dissolution of the Council in 1960. Despite this setback, Hudson Guild continued to work for low and middle-income housing in Chelsea, supporting the International Ladies Garment Workers Union-sponsored Penn Station South Cooperatives, and collaborating with the New York City Housing Authority (NYCHA) in the development of community centers at its Fulton Houses and Chelsea Houses projects. This collaboration led to the replacement of the old Hudson Guild building with a facility in the bottom floors of NYCHA's Chelsea Houses Extension. Opened in 1968, the new Hudson Guild included a gymnasium, theater, and art gallery.
Dan Carpenter retired from Hudson Guild in 1973. He later served as President and Executive of PACT (Provide Addict Care Today), a coalition of labor and business organizations advocating job placement for recovered drug addicts. He continued to live in Chelsea into the 1990s
Scope and Content
The Dan Carpenter Papers document Carpenter's life and career from his boyhood and education in rural Ohio, to his leadership role in the New York City settlement house movement. They offer a unique view of the full career of a professional social worker and influential figure in the Chelsea community, as well as documenting social conditions, demographic change and political activity in New York. In addition, they provide important insight into the life and work of Carpenter's mentor John Lovejoy Elliott.
Carpenter's childhood and early education are best documented by photographs and scrapbooks contained in Series 4 and 5, and by records of his public schooling and attendance at Denison University in Series 1. Correspondence contained in Series 2 provides the most comprehensive view of Carpenter's long career as a social worker and settlement house leader. The impact of Hudson Guild programs on the Chelsea community is documented in Series 1 files on "Chelsea Community Council, "Housing and Urban Renewal," and "Puerto Rican Migration." Papers and speeches in Series 3 demonstrate Carpenter's energetic participation in his professional community, as well as his involvement in numerous Chelsea neighborhood organizations.
Correspondence contained in Series 6 sheds light on the origins of Hudson Guild, and the philosophy and motivation of its founder. Letters by John Lovejoy Elliott to his mother describe his first years in Chelsea, and his early successes and frustrations in establishing Hudson Guild. The series also contains correspondence and biographical information on other members of the Elliott family.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in six series:
Series I: Alphabetical File, 1931-1993
Series II: Correspondence, 1933-1974
Series III: Papers and Speeches, 1934-1972
Series IV: Photographs, 1910-1972
Series V: Scrapbooks and Calendars, 1908-1972
Series VI: Elliott Family Papers, 1880-1962
Subjects
Hudson Guild (New York, N.Y.); LaGuardia Community College.--LaGuardia and Wagner Archives.; Carpenter, Dan.; Moske, James.; New York (N.Y.)--History.; New York (N.Y.)--Social conditions.; Child welfare workers.; Community-based social services.; Community centers--New York (State)--New York.; Human services--New York (State)--New York.; Social advocacy.; Social settlements--New York (State)--New York.; Social service--New York (State)--New York.; Social workers.; Vocational education.; Public welfare--New York (State)--New York.; Administrative records.; Announcements.; Annual reports.; Articles of incorporation.; Brochures.; Budgets.; Bylaws.; Calendars.; Certificates.; Financial records.; Fliers (printed matter).; Legal documents.; Lists.; Memorandums.; Minutes.; Photographs.; Reports.
Access Restrictions
Series I Folder 24 is closed until 2030.
Series II Folders 1 and 2 are closed until 2015.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
Teachers College, Transfer, June 2007.
Finding aid in repository; folder level control.
Related Material
Additional archival materials related to the Dan Carpenter Papers are included in the Hudson Guild Records, as well as in the archival collections of the Ethical Culture Society.
- Series I: Alphabetical File
  Includes correspondence and memos, community organization files, diplomas, news clippings, papers and speeches. Folders arranged alphabetically. Documents arranged chronologically. Folder 24 contains confidential group work case notes and is closed until 2030.
  - Saul Alinsky -Reference Material, 1944-1964 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Saul Alinsky -Reference Material, 1965-1972, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Awards, 1952-1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Biographical Information, 1960-1973 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Chelsea Association for Planning and Action, 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chelsea Community Council, 1955-1959 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Chelsea Community Council, 1960-1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chelsea Community Council, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder F 8)
  - Chelsea Park Opening, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Chelsea Recreation Committee, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chelsea Recreation Committee, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Chelsea Recreation Committee, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Church Information, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Citizens' Union, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Community Control, 1968-1973 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Community Council of Greater New York, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Denison University, 1931-1936 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Denison University, 1956-1973 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Education and Services for Children, 1962-1967 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Encampment for Citizenship, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Fulton Street Property, 1962-1970 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Group Enrollment, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Group Work Education, 1946-1949 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Group Work Reports, 1946-1947 (Box 16, Folder 24)
    [restricted until 2030]
  - Housing and Urban Renewal, 1944-1958 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Housing and Urban Renewal, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Housing and Urban Renewal, nd (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Housing and Urban Renewal -Census Data, 1930s-1950s (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Housing and Urban Renewal -Maps and Plans, 1930s-1950s. (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Housing and Urban Renewal -Reference Material, 1944-1959 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Housing and Urban Renewal -Reference Material, 1962-1969 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Intergroup Relations, 1951-1958 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Juvenile Delinquency, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Mobilization for Youth, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - National Association of Social Workers, 1958-1965 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - National Federation of Settlements, 1932-1968 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - National Recreation School, 1931-1932, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - National Recreation School- Diploma, 1932 (Box 15, Folder 38)
  - New York City Planning Commission -Community Planning Handbook, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - New York School of Printing, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - New York University -Center for Human Relations and Community Studies, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - New York University -School of Education Diploma, 1933 (Box 15, Folder 42)
  - News Clippings (Photocopies):
    - Child Day Care, 1937-1967 nd (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Miscellaneous, 1932-1974 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Puerto Rican Immigration, 1951-1959 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - News Clippings (Originals of photocopies in Folders 43-45). (Box 15, Folder 46)
  - Printers' League of New York, 1946-1956 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Puerto Rican Immigration, 1951-1958. (Box 9, Folder 48)
  - Rotary Club, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Seneca Centaur Club, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 50)
  - Seneca County Public Schools, 1914-1918 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - State of Ohio Teaching Certificate, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Testimonial Dinner, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - United Housing Foundation, 1957-1971 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - United Neighborhood Houses, 1968-1974 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Welfare Issues, 1970-1971 (Box 9, Folder 56)
  - West Side Association of Cornmerce, 1958-1962 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - West Side Award, 1956-1958 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Willard High School, 1924-1926 (Box 9, Folder 59)
- Series II: Correspondence
  Incoming and outgoing letters, memos and attachments. Arranged chronologically. Folders 1 and 2 contain confidential information and are closed until 2015.
  - Michael Clancy, 1933-1948 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    [restricted until 2015]
  - Michael Clancy, 1933-1948 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - General, 1933-1948 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - General, 1951-1955 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - General, 1956 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - General, 1957-1958 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - General, 1959-1960 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - General, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - General, 1962-1964 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - General, 1965 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - General, 1966-1974 nd (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Series III: Papers and Speeches
  Includes drafts and final copies of articles written by Dan carpenter and published by such organizations as the Ethical Culture Society and National Federation of Settlements; also notes, drafts and texts of speeches delivered before Hudson Guild staff meetings, Chelsea community organizations, and professional gatherings. Folders and documents arranged chronologically.
  - Papers and Speeches, 1934-1952 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Papers and Speeches, 1953 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Papers and Speeches, 1954 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Papers and Speeches, 1955 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Papers and Speeches, 1956 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Papers and Speeches, 1957 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Papers and Speeches, 1958 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Papers and Speeches, 1959 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Papers and Speeches, 1960-1961 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Papers and Speeches, 1962 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Papers and Speeches, 1963-1964 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Papers and Speeches, 1965-1972 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Papers and Speeches, nd (Box 12, Folder 13)
- Series IV: Photographs
  - Dan Carpenter -Portraits, ca. 1940-1973 (Folder 27282-27300)
    Black and white photoprints of Dan Carpenter, his family and associates.
  - Dan Carpenter -Special Events, ca. 1935-1973 (Folder 27301-27333)
  - Meyers Family, ca. 1900 (Folder 27334)
  - Unidentified Children, ca. 1910s (Folder 27335-27351)
  - Unidentified House, ca. 1910s (Folder 27352-27362)
  - Unidentified Women, ca. 1910s-1970s (Folder 27363-27369)
  - Fraternity Portrait, ca. 1931 (Folder 27370)
  - Group Portrait Including Dan Carpenter, ca. 1930 (Folder 27371)
  - Willard High School Basketball Team, 1924-1925 (Folder 27372)
  - Willard High School Football Team, ca. 1925 (Folder 27373)
- Series V: Scrapbooks and Calendars
  Scrapbooks contain birthday cards, black and white photoprints, award information, and "This Is Your Life" timeline. Desk and pocket calendars note meetings and appointments. Arranged chronologically.
  - Postcard Scrapbook, 1909-1912 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Postcard Scrapbook, 1909-1918 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - "This Is Your Life," 1956 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Testimonial Dinner, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Desk Calendars, 1968-1972 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Pocket Calendars, 1939-1972 (Box 14)
- Series VI: Elliott Family Papers
  Addresses and writings, correspondence, genealogical information, legal documents, news clippings, publications, and obituaries of Dr. John Lovejoy Elliott and other members of the Elliott family. Folders arranged alphabetically. Documents arranged chronologically.
  - Isaac H. Elliott, 1901-1923 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - John Lovejoy Elliott -
    - Addresses and Writings, ca. 1880 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Addresses and Writings, ca. 1886 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Addresses and Writings, ca. 1908 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Addresses and Writings, The Century, 1924-1925 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Addresses and Writings, The Standard, 1920s-1930s (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Addresses and Writings, "The Settlements of New York and Mr. Reynolds," 1927 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Addresses and Writings, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Birthday, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Birthday Dinner-Dance, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1888-1899 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1900 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1911-1912 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, 1916-1940 nd (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Henry Dreyfuss Booklet, 1922 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Obituary and Memorials, 1942-1972 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Richard S. Elliott Estate, 1941-1949 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Richard S. Elliott Estate, 1953-1962 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Walter W. Elliott, 1948-1950 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Walter W. Elliott Memorial Committee, 1949-1956 (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Ethical Culture Society -The Standard, 1920s-1940s. (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Charles P. Lovejoy, 1914 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Elijah P. Lovejoy, 1897 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Owen Lovejoy, nd (Box 7, Folder 24)
- Name and Subject Index
  - Adler, Felix: Series 6, Folders 11-14, 21 (Box 7)
  - Alinsky, Saul: Series 1, Folders 1-2,7-8 (Box 7)
  - Black, Algernon: Series 6, Folder 20 (Box 7)
  - Cohen, Julius Henry: Series 6 14 (Box 7)
  - Coit, Stanton: Series 6, Folder 12 (Box 7)
  - Dewey, John: Series 6, Folder 14 (Box 7)
  - Lehman, Herbert H.: Series 2, Folder 3 (Box 7)
  - Moses, Robert: Series 2, Folder 3 (Box 7)
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor: Series 2, Folder 3 (Box 7)
  - Wagner, Robert: Series 2, Folder 8 (Box 7)